all right hello and welcome this is
active inference guest stream
87.1 on September 5th
2024 we're here with John Boy and Lee ER
so Lee how about please say hello and
give some
contextualizing thoughts introduce John
however you like and then we'll have
presentation discussion with John so go
for it Lee thank you sure uh thanks
Daniel so um uh I I I came across uh
John through the active INF Institute
because he was the only other person
sitting on the strange intersection that
I'm sitting on in this space between
looking at societal transformation and
active inference as well so I was I was
very excited and um I joined the live
the first live stream that he did on his
science-driven transformation papers um
and subsequently I contacted him and uh
we both explored a kind of a shared
interest I guess in uh functional forms
of cognition at scale and how those can
be facilitated and and John was talking
about the the potential of some kind of
software solution to facilitate that and
uh the kind of the discussion that
ensued over the following months um has
led to a John creating this this paper
so I'm I've kind of been in discussion
with him sort of over the months and I'm
really really interested to uh get more
into this presentation
okay thank you go for it
John thanks Lee appreciate that but I
think it was more like many months of
discussions that uh we were engaged in
that led up to this paper so thanks for
all your input during that
time um so my name is John boy I'm a u a
research fellow at the Active inference
Institute uh very pleased to be uh
appointed that to that position I have
two uh new uh preprints available to the
public uh two papers that we'll be
discussing today uh both on the topic of
um of group cognition at scale as Lee
mentioned uh I'm I'm proposing a a
essentially software ecosystem online
ecosystem for group cognition at scale
and uh and we'll today we'll talk about
kind of the some of the general ideas
there the overview of that project and
then uh on the second guest stream but
maybe is this slides VI can the everyone
see the slides right now and can you go
to the next slide then
please so there's two the two papers
have two guest streams that we're doing
uh today and then the next one is on
September 10th uh and on the second one
today we'll cover some general general
concepts and on the second one we'll get
a little bit more into some technical
details about the underlying meaning
representation uh when we'll I'll
discuss in a moment what that term
meaning representation means but uh this
first paper is available on archive U
you can download the paper from there
and um and let's get started
next slide
please so I'm proposing something called
the cogar ecosystem and cogar stands for
cognitive
narrative and in concept and I and I
should say this is just a concept this
is this project is still in its
incubation phase um uh the the two
papers are the substance of what has
been done so far on this project and I'm
hoping that I can interest others in the
research community and in other
communities Civ Civil Society
communities other communities to uh get
engag with this project and help it to
move
forward so in concept this is an uh
open- Source uh online extensible
ecosystem of basically software but
resources tools applications librar
services that facilitates group
cognition and especially for large
groups um and and especially with regard
to Del deliberation strategizing problem
solving uh decision making and that kind
of things but you'll see that as we go
through these slides you'll see that
there's really a variety of use cases
for this but these are the use cases
that I really had in mind as I was um
developing the concept for the for the
project so essentially cogar helps users
to what I what the way I phrase it is
tell their story and by that I mean to
convey their beliefs to the to what to
to their group about how the world Works
relative to some situation so um a group
can be anything uh could be a you know
could be a um uh could be a a city could
be a corporation could be a school could
be any kind of group that is trying to
you know process the the
understandings and beliefs of its
members towards some goal perhaps
problem solving or some other
goal so in towards that aim cogar helps
users to tell their story that is convey
their beliefs to the group about how the
world works and I both I use the word
story and I use the word narrative in
the in the series the series of two
papers but I don't I don't mean to
confuse the reader because I'm not
talking about a narrative in the normal
sense in the like a written narrative
where you write down several paragraphs
or several pages of text it's this is a
little this is a little different but I
still call the representation of
story because it's it's a story in the
sense that uh that it
conveys users beliefs about like why
something happened and what might happen
next and um what what should we do and
what does it mean and all that kind of
stuff so you know this the this belief
really a belief model that the user is
is creating for this situation maybe
explains you know what is the explains
what the problem is what are we trying
to solve or here's my solution or what
just I think this is what just happened
or what did happen or here's here's what
I think will happen next um here's what
I here's what I think will the people
that will be affected by this issue uh I
believe that so and so and so and so was
involved uh I I think that this this
situation means such and such and we
should take you know to address it we
could take these series of actions or I
think I think this should be done or or
we could learn this from the situation
so it's a story in in the sense that it
it it spans the who what where how why
questions regarding some
situation um next slide
please so uh there's actually several
sort of services and apps available for
for for um group collaboration for
example um uh voting apps and things
like that
um this the Cog our ecosystem is I would
say a much more sophisticated uh uh
approach to that and um it allows a user
to tell what I call what I uh refer to
as as a potentially Rich story that that
means the story could be long complex
nuanced uh it could be conditional like
for example I might believe that in some
situation uh if if we do a and b then
perhaps c will happen but if D happened
first then I then something else is
going on so it could be a conditional
story um could be the could be uh the
equivalent of maybe a few paragraphs of
text very short a story or a story could
be the equivalent of a book chapter you
know it all depends on what the user
wants to
do so so how could such Rich information
be processed by a large
group uh uh that's the really the
question behind cogar how how could how
could that happen so the proposal is for
includes a back-end computational system
that does numerous things it assists
users and in creating and constructing
stories it helps the group to digest
what all of these stories are saying and
how they are the same and how they're
different and
you know what interesting points you
know other stories make and where
there's agreement and you know what are
the what are the many ways that this
issue is seen by this group of
people um so it does like analytics on
stories for example to help answer some
of those questions uh the system also
assesses stories for Quality like you
know is this is this
story uh on topic for whatever the group
is trying to do whatever the whatever
the situation is the group is addressing
uh is it complete does it does the story
just make sense in and of itself um and
um and the the the system can use the
that those kinds of Assessments to give
feedback to the user like uh for example
the a story might have some character in
it named Bob and some other character
named Sue and it might not be clear from
what the user is cre in whether how
those two people are related so the
system might if the system is confused
about what the relationship is it might
actually ask them like ask the user like
what is I'm not I'm a little confused
what's the relationship between these
two people so in that sense the system
is acts very much like a like an Engaged
active listeners like if you were home
telling your story to a friend the
system is kind of like that friend that
is listening and trying to make sense of
what you're saying and maybe asking you
know pertinent questions to help direct
your uh your telling of the story so
that it understands what's what what the
story is
about and the system also performs
inference for uh uh for queries like
perhaps other users other people in the
group have a question for the for the
Storyteller or the story or perhaps the
system has questions like what's the
relationship between Bob and Sue as I
just mentioned
so the system has to perform various
kinds of inference to to help generate
and answer those types of
queries without without such a
computational system the the you know
the the imag Imagine A large group of
thousands of people and thousands of
people submit a long complicated story
how would a group make sense of that if
there weren't some kind of comput
computational system doing assessments
and inference and and uh guidance and
assistance kind of behind the
scenes next
slide so I've been talking about a group
uh a group that's interested in some
some topic some situation or topic or
problem but maybe we should uh take a
moment and and
just let me explain what what I mean by
group so so we're talking about a group
of people in this case and um and I I
call I call a group a collection of
people that demonstrate some kind of
coord coordinated behavior in response
to Dynamic conditions as as time elapses
and conditions evolve so examples
include just about anything you can
think of that would be a a group so
Social Clubs volunteer groups Civic
organizations nonprofits
corporations and even political entities
like uh cities and states and
Nations um a group can range from very
informal to formal flexible to
structured temporary to permanent small
to large autocratic to democratic and
the way it uh it uh manages information
and manages
decision-making
and so a group senses it a group does
many things you know generally a group
has a purpose it form for some purpose
and to carry out its purpose it
generally senses its World processes
information anticipates outcomes uh like
the a group might say you know we we we
should take steps A and B in order to be
financially viable or you know some such
thing it a group evaluates its options
it makes decisions and then it takes
actions uh either just within the group
or within the world or in some way some
kind of actions so in other words I'm
saying that a group can be thought of as
an
organism an organism that performs
cognition and just like any organism an
animal a rabbit a human uh the animal
has to do all of these things it has to
sense it sense its World sense danger in
particular look for food it has to
process the information that it receives
from the world and some of that
information of course can be um
uh you know noisy like it thinks it sees
a wolf but maybe that's not a wolf what
does it do what what should the animal
do in this situation you know it has to
anticipate the outcomes of its actions
evaluate options make decisions and then
take some kind of action in order to in
order to maintain itself in the world
and really in order to thrive in the
world if that's
possible so so I'm I'm thinking of a
group as an thinking of a group is an
organism and that organism is just like
any organism is performing
cognition next
slide so that that's a quick overview of
cogar but uh now you know maybe it's a
good point just to ask the question you
know who cares or more in particular why
should you care the The
Listener um
so uh
obviously cogar is about group
cognition um and maybe you see the need
for improved cognition maybe maybe in
particular you wish that some group
perhaps a political group a nation or a
state or or a corporation or some other
group maybe you have a story to tell
that you think would be important to
help this group out to help the people
to protect to to to warn of danger to
highlight a problem or or a solution
that you think no one else is thought
thought of or is being
underrepresented uh so maybe you have
beliefs a maybe you have a story to sh
share with a group and you want and not
only that it's not just sharing a story
because because if I I could write a a
50-page letter and send it to my
congressman or you know some other some
other group me group or group member and
there's really no guarantee that that
group will really understand what I'm
saying in this in this thing you know
that's um so you so whatever you share
with a group you want them to you want
the group to actually hear it to
register it to hear it and then
understand what it is that you're saying
because why bother if uh why bother com
submitting information if if it if it's
not really heard or
understood or maybe you maybe you look
at the world as as I do and you see that
the world has some serious uh you know
the human world has some serious issues
to solve climate change would be one
example but there's many but pollution
climate change poverty you know all
kinds of social problems and uh and
maybe uh maybe you feel that you know
isn't there some way that we could do
better isn't there some way that as a
groups as as small groups as large
groups as formal groups as informal
groups as is there some way that we
could cognate better that we could be uh
more functional organisms group
organisms and better a better make
better decisions on our world and take
better
actions you know may maybe maybe you
think we could do better or maybe you
just are a scientist and you're
interested just simply in the science
behind cogar and and I would say that
this project is large uh it's and
complex and it touches or or could touch
really just about every field of science
uh I mean if you give me a scientific
field I could could take a a guess as to
how this cogar project might affect it
or or how it incorporates ideas from
that field let's just take one example
say medicine like you might think like
what what what do what what could what
would cogar have to do with medicine
because it's not a medical program you
know in and of itself but doctors have
to make decisions groups uh groups of
doctors insurance companies other groups
have to make decisions so that they have
to come together as a group to make a
decisions and and assess some situation
so that's one potential way another
another potential impact on medicine is
as a patient I have a story to tell I
have a story about what happened um uh
you know there was an accident I I I cut
my arm the I stepped on a nail it was
Rusty this and this you know this and
this happened and I'm I'm afraid of this
and this and I have a condition past
condition of this and this and I'm
allergic to this and this and all of
that can just be written on a piece of
paper you know as a like a regular
intake form but but um in
cogar that the story is standardized in
a sense so that it's easily readable and
understandable by humans and computers
and your any a story that a patient is
telling using a the cogar system would
be um more accessible to inference and
computation and um and there would be
and also there's a natural record of of
of stories in cogar so there would be
potentially many areas of medicine as
just one example of uh of how either
kagar incorporates the science or could
affect the
science um or maybe you're just curious
about uh you know what's possible for
human groups you know we we live in a
society that uh is faces all kinds of
challenges uh there's future challenges
on the
horizon uh you know what what is the
potential of society how
how considering that a society is a
group of people so again we're talking
about groups how C how could How could a
society
best share information make decisions uh
cognate really how could the organism
called a
society perform functional cognition or
or or improved cognition over what is
common or available today so I I I hope
there's many reasons why you might
care about cogner um next slide
please so I've mentioned the term large
group already so you know what does
large group mean what does it mean to
me dozens question mark hundreds
thousands millions of participants and
uh I would say the answer is yes all of
those right um maybe dozens of people
perhaps can fit in a room excuse me fit
in a room and and talk freely about some
situation some topic and uh and share
Rich information verbally or you know in
other ways face to
face that might work with dozens but uh
it doesn't work so well with hundreds uh
and it certainly doesn't work so well
with thousands or Millions so um as I
said a moment ago cogar has many
potential use cases but but one that I'm
really targeting is the large group
setting where really you know hundreds
to thousands or millions of people are
um are involved in the group and and
having said that there's also use cases
for just a single person using cogar
there would be reasons why somebody
might want to record their story in
cogar just for personal reasons to as a
history for example to look back on
later and reflect when and there's other
reasons to that we'll talk about
shortly so so the question at hand is
you know what kind of online ecosystem
would allow say a 100,000 people to
share some kind of Rich uh complex story
and and in particular Dynamic story like
I I I'm a member of a group we're
sharing our stories I I write down what
my story is I I look at what you're
writing I look at your story and I go oh
that's a I like that idea I like that
part of it or that's that seems really
useful to me or oh I forgot I forgot
yeah that I should have mentioned that
myself so by sharing stories by sharing
belief models we can come to um you know
uh uh reach a you know better agreement
our our belief by sharing our belief
models can start to um influence one
another and and de and the group then
develops a shared belief model to an
extent um and then and then it's not
just about sh cogar is not just about
sharing
uh uh stories it's about using them in
some kind of to fa to facilitate
functional group cognition right so you
can imagine a group
Corporation any kind of group Civic
group um a city state and the cognition
for that group you might say is
functional sometimes or really quite
dysfunctional sometimes So Co cogar is
is aiming at facilitating functional
group cognition that's its
purpose uh next next
slide okay so um we've talked about what
a group is uh and I've not and I've used
the word cognition now many times so
maybe we should talk about what is
cognition um
so in cognitive science one might come
up with very definitions of you know
what is cognition how does it work what
is its purpose so I'm relying quite
heavily on the active inference uh uh
framework for the you know my definition
of cognition and and the way the cogn
system would work but active inference
is uh is essentially a basian
description of cognition it's a
normative principle uh under writing
cognition and and biological and
artificial
agents so in active inference there's an
intelligent agent and a world that the
intelligent agent is acting in maybe
maybe there's even multiple intelligent
agents acting in the world and an agent
has an internal generative model about
how the world Works uh that is it it it
it given some
conditions um it sees that the that
there's potential actions that could be
taken and it and it sees that there's
likely outcomes of various actions so uh
an agent has a model of of how the world
Works what would ha what will happen if
I do a what will happen if I do B
what'll happen if I don't run from that
lion um and uh the the the the the the
agent and its world are separated in a
sense statist statistically separated by
what's called a mark blanket and that
blanket uh consists of agent actions and
agent observations so as an agent I take
some action that action affects the
world the world reacts in some way
according to the world's generative
process and then things change
conditions change and as an agent I
perceive the my world but you know maybe
it's dark and I don't perceive it very
closely or maybe it's loud and I don't
hear it very accurately or you know I
get Sensations from the world but
they're not necessarily I'm not
necessarily observing the actual state
of the world I'm observing some kind of
noisy representation of
that so uh so the the act the Markov
blanket is a it's it's it's
conditionally separates the world from
the
agent uh and active inference is the
framework that I'm using to to talk
about cognition uh and and not just
cognition how it works but also what is
the purpose of cognition what is what is
functional cognition versus
dysfunctional
cognition NE uh next slide
please so what is the purpose of
cognition well from an active inference
perspective it's we can think of it you
know simply as an idea realiz four part
four-part CYCC process of I I predict
what will happen if I act I I choose an
action from my generative model I I the
world changes I sense whatever however
the world has changed and I learn from
processing those sense sense inputs for
example uh suppose I'm a young boy and
I'm learning how to catch a baseball
right if I don't lift my arm high enough
I maybe miss the ball so that happens a
few times I I learn that I really need
to lift my arm higher if I want to catch
that ball so uh
so you know again uh informally and
simply it's the cycle of predict act
sense and learn and an agent does this
it it engages in cognition to reduce its
uncertainty be un certain about whether
it's going to maintain achieve and
maintain those conditions that it's
thinks will be good for it that will
that will help it's thriving as a as a
young boy learning how to catch a ball I
I want to catch the ball that will be
good for me if I can learn how to catch
a baseball and I want to I want to
reduce my uncertainty that I'm going to
catch that ball I'm going to practice
hard and I'm going to learn from my
mistakes and I'm going to reduce the
uncertainty that when I put my glove up
that ball is going to land on it
or or I'm GNA out outsmart the Lion and
get and get away from danger when the
lion appears uh so an an agent favors
those choices those actions that are and
G that are going to ensure the greatest
resolution of uncertainty under the
constraint that preferred outcomes are
realized that's the way friston phrases
it so so you know so you know it's it's
it's not just that I want to learn how
to catch a ball or run from a line it's
that I want to
sure or pretty sure that I can catch
that ball or or get out of the way of
that
line and uh and from all this I would
say that active inference offers a
potential description of functional
versus dysfunctional cognition if if if
I have a pattern of making poor
predictions and therefore acting in ways
that are that are harmful to me I you we
could call that dysfunctional cogn if if
I fail to remember what happened last or
fail to remember how many times or the
many ways that I missed the ball uh that
could be also called dysfunctional
cognition and cognition itself rests on
many core uh functionalities like
remembering and attention and and uh and
communication and other other you know
processes and any one of those all of
them together and anyone in in
individually could be functional or
dysfunctional in some you know cognitive
event uh next slide
please so so given all of that
background what what is the cogar
ecosystem
really
so I'm G to I'm going to I'm going to
claim or offer that the that cogar could
be viewed as a cognitive architecture
so every organism has some kind of every
organism cognates whether it's a amoeba
or a human and um cogn cognition
requires some sort of cognitive
architecture uh for humans we have a
central nervous system and and we also
have computers and external tools and
things that can be thought of as part of
that cognitive
architecture and uh the cognitive
architecture essentially integrates
information and and helps us coordinate
our actions in the world and it's the
and it's the set of components by by
which and through which cognition occurs
and for a group that includes uh the a
group as members so it includes the
cognitive architecture of the individual
members but it also includes the the the
the set of norms that a group uses its
rules its mechanisms and institutions
its tools it's its
sensors perhaps we're talking about a
group that is a nation and it has
sensors on air pollution you know
something like that uh it's analytic
processes its systems procedures all of
which uh facilitate or guide cognition
really make cognition possible and every
part of a cognitive architecture can be
functional or dysfunctional right so for
a group say um maybe it's rules maybe it
has certain rules that that are either
enhance functional cognition or or
detract from functional cognition so I I
view cogar as a component of the
cognitive archit architecture of the
groups that are using it and again its
purpose is to facilitate functional
cognition versus dysfunctional
cognition uh next slide oh lee
yeah yeah hi John um sorry this is
really interesting because um you know
based on the discussions we've been
having uh I'm kind of using the concept
of cognitive architecture in some of the
research that I'm doing in organizations
at the at the minute and um and Tred to
feed it back in So if you take a um an
organization like a public sector body
or a a commercial
organization um would you would you
consider that the the the structure of
the processes are all part part of the
the cogn cognitive architecture of that
particular
entity well I mean I suppose depending
on how broadly you want to define a an
architecture I suppose it can include
just about every aspect of a group you
know potentially but I think in a
practical sense you could probably focus
on those components of group type of you
know those mechanisms and structures of
the group and its dynamics that would be
particularly aimed at uh sensing the
really the four steps that I uh
discussed just a minute ago U taking
action learning uh you know sensing the
world uh you know one of the things I
guess one of the reasons I ask is is one
of the things that uh tends to the the
context in organization has a an
enormous influence in shaping people's
behavior um but uh because there's a
there's a general kind of widespread
view that cognition is localized within
people rather than a kind of a you know
an organismic view of it I guess where
it's kind of distributed between people
um in a hierarchical organization a lot
of those factors if I mean I'm almost
viewing it now as a as a generative
model but there's no way that certain
processes that determine Behavior can
actually be subject to change because
they're not considered as part of the
cognitive structure if you if you see
what I mean so I think the idea um you
know that that um groups could view
themselves as organisms is really
interesting but currently there's kind
of more of a mechanistic kind of view of
of organizations and I think that
potentially gets in the way anyway maybe
this is a discussion for a for a
different no no no no no no no it's
actually good because I I I I I I wanted
to
emphasize the importance of this view
you know thinking of a group as an
organism as a cognitive organism and
thinking of decision making and and
those operations as aspects of group
cognition so you
know uh the world is kind of crazy in
some ways politics are engaging for many
people and this is just one example in
the in the for political entity but you
know we
we we rarely ask ask what a u what a
economic system is supposed to do or
what a governance system is supposed to
do or or really what an organization is
supposed to do right so so what we're
framing all of that now in terms of
cognition and we're framing it in such a
way that it is amenable to Scientific
you know examination of whether this is
functional or dysfunctional and and
we're and and from an active infer
inference perspective cognition has a
purpose so so then we can start talking
about is this organization the you know
it structures the way it the way
it's put together its rules its
mechanisms its institutions fun is that
functional yeah and and could right and
could it be improved like now that we
know what we're after now that we have
the problem you know the the issue in
Focus yeah how could we improve the the
cognition of of uh I just give you a
tiny little tiny little vignette so in
this particular organization they have a
performance management system uh but the
so that if you if you to take the view
of functional cognition you go the
purpose of the you know what's the
purpose of the performance management
system what it's there to motivate
employees reward them you know make them
feel excited about their work but it
doesn't do any of that what it actually
does is it demoralizes them annoys them
gets in their way and just generally
pisses them off I mean it's actually
doing the opposite of what's intended
you take the whole system out and the
organization would be better off but
there's no it's not subject to any
prediction error signal because it can't
be no ever defined it in terms of you
know purpose and outcome so it's a
completely dysfunctional system that's
just stuck there that you can't take out
and nobody you know nobody has a view on
it it's it's really weird but I think
would really get to it but anyway sorry
to interrupt the no no no no no it's
it's good it's good I I just want to
emphasize again that this is a in a
sense it's a change in world viw it's a
this is
a comprehensive and potentially very
useful way to con to understand what a
group is whether that group is a small
informal group or a large formal group
and and and then to assess you know how
well it's doing and how could how could
we how could it do
better right so this that's the question
for cogar that I raised just a minute
ago is like okay given the setup given
our goals given the purpose of cogar so
what kind how should cogar be designed
you know like how should it how should
it be designed to do what we're saying
it should do you know that's the
question
here um but anyway but getting back to
the back to where we were at in the
slides uh cogar is I I would say cogar
is a part of the cognitive architecture
of the group that's using
it next
slide so
actually this this slide speaks lead to
some of the some of the things that you
were raising there and and it speaks to
some of the um some of the things that I
just mentioned but so consider a society
as a group let say a nation as a group
again a a group that is that is an
organism performing cognition for some
purpose and that purpose obviously for
any organism is to thrive to to maintain
viability to to do well to Live pass on
information um so in the I I've wrote a
series of uh of three papers a couple of
years ago in 2020 and 21 2021 and I
think maybe there's I don't know Daniel
four guest streams for that series I
think three or four or something like
that that are in the archives so I
encourage viewers to check those out too
um and that series of three
papers again looked at cognitive
architecture only in this case it looked
at uh societal systems as the cognitive
architecture of a society so by core
societal systems I mean for example e
economic systems Financial systems
governance systems legal systems
Educational
Systems you know these
constitute a
considerable aspect of the cognitive
architecture for society we use these
systems to sense the world to think to
make decisions to allocate resources to
take a variety of actions uh that that
hopefully actions that better the you
know the nation at
hand so um societies around the world or
nations around the world have I should
really say Nations around the world have
some kind of the core societal systems
say economic systems that have some kind
of particular design to them for
financial system as a particular design
but the question I raise in this paper
is
in the series of papers is out out of
all conceivable
designs you
know existing designs or completely new
designs which which of them might be
most fit for this purpose of group
cognition which of these might best
serve the common good and and and
obviously making good decisions that you
know favor the vitality and well-being
of a nation is serving the common good
so out of any conceivable design for
economic systems you
know what is money for example is there
some other way to think about money or
some other alternative to money or how
do votes happen or you know like any
aspect of a core societal
system one could imagine many
conceivable variations on on a theme or
just completely new designs new new ways
of looking at what an economic system is
and from this umbrella of considering
all of these systems as part of a part
of a a cognitive architecture then one
can then one can ask you know really
what designs are fit for purpose and how
do we of course how do we measure
Fitness and you know what kind of
information goes into assessing the
fitness of some system but it opens the
door for a science-based design of the
systems by which societies live under
and that is not the way that is not the
you know our current system economic
system Financial systems governance
systems they were not you know developed
through some kind of science-based
process they were they kind of evolve
through social social pressures and
social conditions and and you know ideas
from individuals and but
we could revisit all of that um and and
ask the question you know what what what
designs actually would serve Us best and
in the series I propose an R&D program
to really to address that very question
not just not just you know the not just
as an academic exercise of you know
let's write some interesting papers
about you know how how governance
systems could be redesigned
the idea in this uh series is how do you
what kind of designs would potentially
be most useful and then how do you test
them actually practically test them
Implement them use them you know gain
information from you know the the
experience of of using them and learning
and learn from them how how how could
that happen how could that actually be
done how could some kind of
transformation you know I call it
transformation in the series but how
could some kind of transformational step
like that
occur and be viable and practical so in
the in the series I offer you know I
what I think is One path towards that
but this current uh uh series of two
papers that we're discussing today this
is an it's an extension of the same idea
it's again looking at the cognitive
architecture of a group and asking the
question uh in this case for cogar what
kind of design of cogar would could best
help uh group
cognition and how could cogar be used by
groups to you know to help
them perform better
cognition next next
slide you know now that I've said next
slide but there's just one more thing I
want to say about the last slide uh uh
you as I was about to say a few minutes
ago lots of people are interested in
politics and you know what a government
should do and and they have ideas for uh
you know like maybe somebody thinks that
uh that um term limits on a for judges
or for politicians should be limited
that you know that that would be a you
know that might be a solution to some of
our problems or you know there's all
kinds of of um proposals floating around
for how to improve economic systems or
governance systems or you
know any any of the core societal
systems
and and even say corporations do the
same thing you know they wonder how
could we improve our Communications and
all that kind of stuff
but this concept this this this this
really powerful approach of viewing
systems as a as a cognitive architecture
allows those questions to become you
know meteor in a way you know more
relevant more with a greater high level
understanding of what that system is
actually supposed to do so I I believe
that by viewing the the societal systems
of a society as a cognitive AR
architecture and looking at groups as as
you know small or large groups as uh as
as organisms that perform cognition I
think that opens up all kinds of doors
and avenues for investigation into what
kinds of designs what kinds of you know
rules and and approaches and methods and
tools might actually uh help groups
perform better cognition and and better
solve their problems okay next
slide so um everything we've talked
about so far has just been sort of high
level what is cogar what is it do what
is it purpose but uh this slide really
gets more to the to the question of how
does Scot work you like under the
hood so I I I've already said that I use
the word story but I don't mean story in
the regular sort of narr written
narrative sense uh uh a user creates a
story excuse me creates a story but and
and it creates a story May perhaps by
speaking you know in one version of
cogner maybe a user speaks the story and
the system hears it and understands it
but maybe the first version of cogar
would be uh somebody the user inputs a
story kind of Passage by passage you
know sentence by
sentence and um the system takes that
input those little passages and other
metadata associated with passages and
constructs uh a fragment of a of a of a
story and that story is represented
representative represented has a graph
so it has a its internal meaning
represent representation is called a is
actually called a story
graph and that story
graph the reason that it's not s stored
in just regular English text or text of
some other language is that this
representation
allows is is more amenable to
computation and could be better
understood in the large group setting
that in that sense there's other reasons
too we'll get to but but the important
thing for this slide is that is that
actually what the user is creating is
something that resembles a
graph a graph of how the elements of the
story and are are are uh are are
related and story graphs are really the
core Innovation on which Kar is based
and that it it's that representation
allows cogar to curate understand reason
with perform inference for uh stories
and these stories then represent really
high quality
information uh much of the information
much of the vagueness of natural
language is eliminated in this way not
all the vague vagueness but some of the
vagueness is limited in this way so uh
at the top of this little graph you can
see that a user types in for example
text text passages those are translated
by the system into what I call a story
graph fragment just a small little graph
for that passage and that story graph
fragment is then merged with the growing
larger story graph and um once it's
complete that complete that the complete
story graph can then be translated and
used in various ways it could be
translated back into natural language so
that potentially a user could listen to
their story back like you know I I typed
in this I typed in my story about you
know what should happen for this
particular situation and uh I could ask
the system to replay that back to me and
hear it
perhaps uh it ALS this the story graph
can also be translated or used as input
into a a variety of inference models so
probabilistic logical or other kinds of
models and maybe it would be maybe it
could be translated into alternative
meaning representations that would be
useful in certain kinds of inference
models so that's what happens under the
hood you're constructing in a story
graph and you can view the user can view
aspects of that graph as it's
constructed to verify that the system
actually understood correctly what I'm
trying to
say uh next slide
please oh uh well fine this is good um
so this is an example of a meaning
representation a very common meaning
representation called the abstract
meaning representation for a particular
sentence uh sentences a similar
technique is almost always is almost
impossible to apply to other crops such
as cotton sowing beans and rice so so
you can see that this sentence the the
representation is structured uh there's
rules for how the representation is
constructed and there's a structure to
it and certain links arrows lines
between uh nodes have you know a given
meaning um and um I I I have this in the
paper and here just really just as as an
example of what a what I would call a
relatively simple uh meaning
representation might look like so the
cogar meaning representation is going to
be like this only far more sophisticated
um in in many ways so for just as one
example um anticipation and predictions
are an important very important part of
cognition as we've already
discussed and the meaning representation
has to be you know sophisticated enough
to handle the predictions of a of a
story of a belief system like if if the
uh if if the topic at hand is uh
immigration um I have a beliefs about
you know what kind of rules the
immigration Authority should have and
how it should be done and you know build
a wall or don't build a wall this just
one of the topics of of conversation in
the in the papers these days
um um but for my story uh there would be
naturally would be uh anticipations and
and predictions related like uh uh I if
we build a wall then it will have such
and such an effect if we don't build a
wall it'll have such and such an effect
if we allow Freer immigration it'll have
such and such an effect these are all
anticipations predictions and the
meaning representation has to be
sophisticated enough to handle all those
and they're not just and they're not
just um predictions they're
probabilistic predictions no one knows
what's going to happen in the future so
all of those kinds of statements are are
probabilistic so even even you know it
has to be even more the meaning
representation has to be sophisticated
enough to handle probabilistic uh
predictions about you know what a story
means and what might happen next so uh
this is a very simple graphical version
just to give you the user a very very
high Lev rough idea of what's going on
under the hood but in the actuality the
cogar meaning representation would would
be much more
sophisticated next
slide so um what is the purpose of the
story graph some of this I've mentioned
uh already but uh it represents a story
in a format that is less ambiguous than
natural language natural language can be
very ambiguous very U it the story graph
is meant to be readable and
understandable both by humans and
computers so a human can look at a story
graph or pieces of a story graph views
of a story graph and uh and and and
verify that the system understood the
story correctly for example but
computers then can also read and process
the stories and then you know perform
analytics and inference and do do the
many things that the back and the
computational system has to
do the stories obviously then provide a
structure for inference and Analysis and
they also serve as intering lingua uh to
you know a natural language independent
representation that's suitable from for
translations into other languages or uh
uses inputs to analytical models or
other
things so that's what a story graph
should do and then one of the questions
is well what what what does the cogar
story graph you know what is its design
you know what is the what are the
specifics of its design and that is a
topic that I raise in the in the second
paper that we'll talk about a little bit
in the next uh guest room next slide
please so um we've talked about stories
and I've I've said a little bit about
what what they are but let's maybe recap
that just a bit so you know a use has
some story in their head about a
situation some you know issue or problem
in the world and um and the user has an
internal belief model about how the
world Works relative to that situation
or problem and a story is a is a is an
externalization of of that belief model
so and that and it and it potentially is
a dynamic externalization you know it
can change as the user sees other
stories or reads what other people think
um so it it it externalizes a user's
belief system and makes it sharable you
know that's the purpose of cogar is to
share these belief models with other
members of the group uh so again it the
story conveys a user's beliefs and the
the emphasis here is on beliefs right
because um the the comput the
computational system is not going to
predict what's going to happen in real
life if the group takes actions a versus
action B for example uh and it's not
going to the system is not going to
verify that somebody's story is AC is
accurate is realistic or or is practical
for the situation at hand those are
those are assessments that the group of
users has to do you know together and
the system helps that process but it
doesn't perform those kinds of uh
assessments so so the system the system
doesn't have to know the rules of
gravity or you know Newtonian mechanics
or it doesn't have to predict what's
going to happen in the world it it re
all the system needs to do is to capture
a user's belief model and to communicate
that model with others and to help
others help the group
understand that model and how it
compares to other models and um what
elements are in it and you know what is
its time span and you know what what is
what what is this you know what are the
characteristics of this user's belief
system and and what is the user
predicting will happen so it's it's the
story just captures the user's beliefs
right and then the Group shares and acts
in some way on those
beliefs so so that's it the the system
helps a group to understand what its
members believe that's that's really the
core of this
and then those by sharing those beliefs
users can uh influence one another
perhap you know like in a
decision-making
setting next slide
please all right so uh so we've talked
about what a story is how it's
represented of an under the hood what
it's what the purpose of cogar is what
the purpose of a story is and now we can
talk about how this cogar system might
be actually used and I've said that the
emphasis is on you know the cognition in
the large group setting and particularly
for things like decision making and and
collaboration and things like that but
in actuality there's a very wide span of
use cases that are possible with this
kind of
ecosystem um and and I'll cover just a
few possibilities but I but these are
non this is a non-exhaustive list
there's many many possibilities and the
communications in in its different uses
you know may maybe there's an app
developed for each particular kind of
use but so maybe there's many apps that
are part of the ecosystem but the but
this but the sort of events I I call it
a group event aoup a group a group
defines an event and then invites people
to participate in the event so for
example a city might if a city is using
the system it might um um Define a group
event to solve some particular issue
maybe a trash issue or recycling issue
or a road issue or some other issue and
the and the group would Define the topic
for the event and the purpose of the
event and the rules for the event and
the methods for the event and how
decisions we made and you know the setup
for how this event is going to unfold
and then it asks for a group input
through story
graphs so depending on the event and the
group and the purpose of the event the
communications can be many to many as in
you know
collaborative decision- making for
example they could be many to one or
even one to many so uh and and and and
I've been emphasizing group use but
again an individual might use this just
for their own personal use just to
record their their understandings of the
world at a certain time for
example so some possible use cases are
in decision-making such as by a
corporation or decision uh Corporation
or city uh maybe customer service
uh emergency reports public polling
instructions for how to put together
bookshelves or instructions for how to
run a machine for example uh system
descriptions of you know what is what is
this system and how does it work or
maybe there's whole variety of
educational uh use cases also and uh
later versions of cogar could be could
include things like a role playing or
game playing like uh intentional games
uh purpose games and strategizing what
what what here's here's my belief system
of the world relative to the situation
and uh you know the people involved in
the story or the characters involved in
the story or you know so and so and so
and so and so and so and what would
happen if I if I take action a you know
what's likely to be the outcome what is
what is player b g to likely to do if I
take action a so later more
sophisticated versions of cogn Might
include that kind of stuff where you
user might play against the system or
two systems in a sense might play
against each other to as to to you know
to to strategize for some
situation um next
please so the next couple of slides are
just a few examples that I have in the
paper and um for use cases so I'll cover
them briefly uh um so I have written at
the top of these slides
some text and this isn't actually the
text that you know somebody would uh
write in a in the real codar this is
just a snippet an example snippet of the
kind of information that a user might
want to convey right so this user
there's an issue some issue X and this
this this person believes that in order
to address that we should first address
issue why that caused X and why started
when you know it's it when such and such
happened and it had the effect of such
and such and this person believes that
if we don't solve issue y then some
event a some unwanted event a is likely
to occur maybe within a few months and
then ex the original issue is going to
be impossible to
solve so if that if a happens then you
know there's going to be all these
effects maybe you know and there's some
this this in the story there's some kind
of uh you know uh
20% value put on the risk of this or or
the or the outcome of this and uh this
user says a possible solution to this
this problem why is to do you know such
and such and it's conditional so do such
and such if event B occurs and such and
such if event C
occurs so there's some kind of you know
complicated story conditional story
involved here that has predictions in it
um it's it's uh you know there some
shoulds in it you know we should do this
uh and how does how does how does all
that work uh for the decision-making
case well one common I I believe what
would be a common setup for the
decision-making case is um uh a group
forms comes together for an event and
individuals you know create their story
that's kind of at the top of this
diagram they create their story and then
um you know submit their story and the
system the middle the middle block
though the system does its assessments
and computations and you know the
various things that the system is going
to do and then it reports back to the
group about the range of stories that
have been submitted and what they
include and who they involve and you
know what the kinds of of solutions are
have been proposed and the various kinds
of summaries and details about about the
the set of sto that have been involved
and then the group uh uh you know
digests that information and looks at
individuals can look at individual other
the the stories of other
individuals uh so users can kind of take
in what the group is saying and maybe a
user thinks oh that's that's you know
Bob had something really interesting to
say there and I you know I should really
include that as part of my story that
was a good idea I didn't include it so
should includeed so um the next step is
a this this process uh Cycles in a
series of rounds and at the end of each
round there's a kind of dialogue and
digestion phase where everyone looks at
what's been done and gets a better idea
of what the group is thinking and maybe
they adjust their their story uh you
know accordingly and hopefully over time
over a series of rounds the a proposed
solution that the group favors starts to
become clear right and then then this
process can end when it's sufficiently
clear and there's enough agreement that
we we understand each other we we think
we understand the situation and we think
as a group that this you know this this
this this solution or this set of
solutions might uh be the best to
actions to
take and so that's the that's group
decision- making might occur over a
series of rounds uh next
slide here's a an example use case for
emergency reports this is a this is a
person who wants to report that they
just witnessed an accident uh there's an
accident with some kind of truck of some
kind uh maybe it was going too fast
maybe it was because of the wet
conditions it shouldn't have been going
so fast uh lots of accid like side
information there's been many accidents
at that corner so maybe that that maybe
the the uh maybe the local conditions
have something to do with this but
anyway the the truck had a telephone
pole and now there's Sparks and the
grass and uh there's a school and
children are playing outdoors and um you
know all of this is a little unclear to
me I'm about a block away but um you
know that's what I see and I report it
so you know there's a there's an
interesting story and and you could
imagine even a more complex story of
someone that wants to report report
something maybe they want to report a
crime for example or in this case an
emergency report and there's also
there's various kinds of inference that
has to happen like under the hood for
this right like if you read the the
sentences that I that I wrote there I
never say that a uh
wire uh fell from the lines and is now
on the grass that's sort of inferred
right so there's various things that the
that the the system has to infer about
this story in order to make sense of it
and I say that there's uh you know this
user is saying that there's children
present but the implication is is that
there's a danger to those children right
so there there's actually a forecast
like a prediction like if we don't do
something someone might get hurt so
these children might be harmed you know
because of the a the uh you know the
aftermath of this
accident um so uh
so uh you know this is this is this is a
this little story is a lot different
than for example calling a hotline and
the hotline instructs you to press one
if there's a fire press two if there's a
you know some something else and then if
you press one for a fire it says you
know press one if um the fire is in your
house press two if you know whatever
so there are other computations systems
out in the world that seek to address
seek to gather this kind of information
you know for for the purpose of making
an emergency report but I'm claiming
that out of all out of all the kinds of
systems that I know of the cogar system
is much more functional and has the
capacity to convey a much
richer uh story understanding of
someone's understanding about about a
situation and perform inference on it
and record as a history the story and
how it evolved and many other things
that the that the computational system
does
offers next slide
please um this is a uh this is an
example for customer service this is an
example of a of a U of A many toone sort
of communication right in the sense of
um
many customers are are communicating
with one agent one one Central agent
which is the corporation in this case so
uh uh people are are writing in and
they're sending in their broken parts
and they're you know they're they're
giving a description of why this part
worked or you know is this part
defective or why was this why was this
aspect of the part designs seemingly so
poorly or could you fix this design or
you know like here's what here's what's
here's where it's broken this this part
here this this Part F has a leak in it
and it causes this other part H to slip
you know some kind of sliding mechanism
to slip and uh and you know seems to me
that part was it wasn't really broken
it's just that it didn't really fit so
was that by Design or is this part
defective or you know is what's what's
what's going on here with this so you
know this is Rich information that a
that a corporation might receive about
uh its products from users and uh you
know much more useful than say just a
you know a couple of sentences written
in natural language or maybe a paragraph
written in natural language because you
know the corporation could use this to
really assess you know really
analyze
uh
closely uh uh what what what's going on
and how many times does this happen and
how many times have people complained
that that part was too thin and you know
all that kind of stuff so uh so there's
there's an example of a of a of a many
to one sort of communication scheme next
slide this is uh also an example of them
many to one so uh you know lots of
political things happening in the world
right now elections and so on and lots
of polling going on too for the for the
different elections and um you know
typically in polls you might be asked a
yes or no question you know do you agree
with the statement yes or no or maybe
you have a a a short um uh uh multiple
choice you know do yes I agree strongly
or no I disagree strongly or I can rate
my agreement on a scale of one to five
or you know some something like that but
that is not near as rich as as in taking
what the user actually has to say and
what what they what they think are the
important aspects to to this to the
question that's being pulled about in
this case the user is is is there's a
poll for some candidate and uh this user
is saying you know I thought her past
decisions on certain issues were
terrible and I've been fuming about them
and um I don't trust her on this issue
because of such and such statement and I
don't even think she's sincere on that
issue and anywayss that issue could be
solved by some other much simpler
process which you know I'm I I mention
here and uh I don't think I'm GNA vote
for her so you know this is Rich
information and again there's inference
that has to go on behind the scenes with
the with the uh system for example the
word fuming you know that could has
various meanings uh does it mean that
the person the writer is on
fire no not in this it means that
they're angry so out of the various
definitions of the word fuming the
system has to figure out what definition
is the user aiming for
here um next slide and then I think
we're done with the next slide uh where
we come to the end of our talk so uh
what is next for this project uh I've
already mentioned that cogar is in the
incubation phase and um and I put out
the vision in these two papers a vision
for it and um really it's a big project
it touches on many aspects of science
computational science complex system
science all kinds of different Sciences
it touches on and this is all beyond my
capacity as one person to create so if
this project is going to move forward it
it will need your help uh whether you're
a scientist or you're uh belong to a
Civic organization or you're just an
interested citizen or whatever there's
there's there's some way that uh just
about anyone could be involved in this
especially as it picks up steam and and
moves starts to move forward um there's
many many interesting questions to
address I I I raise a few future
research questions in the papers but
there's many many more That Could Be
Imagined and I encourage people to reach
out to me if they have interest in this
project um upcoming there there's the
guest stream on September 10th that's
next Tuesday and um uh I I I believe
I'll be starting a cogar project at the
Active inference Institute as people can
get that involved that way and get
involved with the Institute that way and
uh they there should be some additional
talks coming up there's a active
inference Symposium coming up that I
think I'll present that and um and
there's a few other talks I'll be giving
to to private groups and and such so uh
again please reach out to me if you have
interest in this and uh and uh show up
next time for the for the guest stream
on September 10th and we'll continue the
discussion awesome thank you John I will
read some of the questions from lot chat
upcycle Club wrote is group cohesion one
of the goals of
cogar um so good question and and you
know the the
in any kind of group there may be very
different opinions of what should happen
and um there may be lots of friction in
that group right so um it's not that
cogar is is necessarily going to solve
all kinds of friction problems and get
everybody on the same page for every
setting you know that would that's not
the way the world works right but but
what it what cogar does do is a sets up
a process and a means and a mechanism by
which people can share their stories and
perhaps come to some agreement uh shared
understanding you know share the share
their way they see the world and maybe
the group will come to some kind of
shared understanding if the purpose is
decision-making you know that's kind of
the context here so um hopefully a group
will come to some kind of uh agreement
but but but even if they don't cogar
can cogar has a record of the stories
and of the differences in stories and
maybe there's really kind of two subsets
in this group or three or four subsets
in this group and and each subset views
the situation in a very different way
well at the very least cogar is going to
help the group to understand that
there's you know different ways to look
at this problem and different proposed
Solutions and it's going to record the
the the the evolving stories that are
related to to this you know like how
they how a particular story started and
what it what it r to become over the
course of cognition and um so you know
maybe that maybe the group will actually
come to a a well uh you know widely
accepted uh decision on some topic or
maybe it won't but at least it's going
to have a functional process to you know
to to go through to to understand itself
right so that's the that's the that's
the hopefully yes and but you know that
what happens the Dynamics depends on
what the group is and what the topic is
thank you all right next question from
abis tolge who
wrote two
questions one how does cogar maintain
consistency in story graph updates when
passages are the single source of
record second question how are changes
propagated across the story graph and
Associated models without
conflicts um can use can use um back in
the slides to the to the uh process
process of creating a story it's kind of
far back there one more yeah there we go
this one yeah there you go thank you
okay so
um
so one could imag you know we're
thinking about how should cogar be
designed you know how should how should
it work you know what should it do and
um you know one could imagine
the a users could input text type in
something and then that text becomes a
story graph fragment here and then the
story graph fragment becomes a story
graph and then the re and then maybe the
user realizes oh I I didn't mean that or
I didn't make that clear I want to add
something so how should the user edit
this thing right you could edit the
story graph or you could edit the graph
fragment or you could edit the original
text and then rebuild the story from
there right so how should it
happen well um the simplest approach and
the approach I suggest in the in the
paper is that all the editing really
happen on the text passages because if
if you uh allow edits on the story graph
then they have to propagate in this
diagram have to propagate upward to so
you know to change the original text
passages so that everything is in
agreement all the different sources of
information are in agreement so it would
be easier and simplest if there's only
one source of information and that the
entire graph can be um uh you know
regenerated from that source as the as
the information
changes um what was the second question
I think maybe I answered how how is the
internal consistency and and the
statistical consistency and then also
the the changes of through actual
propagation how does conflict how are
changes propagated across a sto story
graph and Associated models without
conflicts yeah yeah that's that's that's
I think I answered the question or at
least I tried to um so there's only one
source of record and that's the text
passages itself but suppose now that the
that the system uh suppose the user
created a story and the system uh uh
responds and says hey I don't I don't
understand is is you know is Bob Bill's
brother or his boss I don't understand
you know what this relationship is or
who when you say he which he are you
referring to Bob or Bill or you know who
who who is it that this this passage
refers to so now the now you have a
situation
where um you know maybe maybe the
question
is is um are they brothers or are they
co-workers maybe that's the question the
system poses
and maybe the user responds their
brothers you know as a response well how
does that how does that response you
know get into the story graph right
because you don't want the system
to edit the story graph because then the
system would have to change you know
propagate that changed information back
up into the text passages and that might
not work so well you know what if the
system doesn't propagate it
correctly uh the user could simply
change their original text passages and
and and make clear that what the
relationship is you know what whatever
the question is so you know that's a
clear way us just changes the text
passage itself but another way is
there's some there's metadata associated
with a text passage and that metadata
might actually be you know include the
kind of the conversation between the
user and the and the and the system the
system says the system asks you know are
they brothers or co-workers and the
users's response is they're co-workers
okay well that that's meta information
that is now you know saved as meta
information and can be become part of
the graph you know
Downstream what about the human element
of conflict like using Code as law legal
code plain text repositories versioning
and forking and
instancing how does the social reality
of the conflict
not go into the fractal Linux
kernel separation and what would
actually you said one version of record
and whether or not that resolves logical
ambiguity that's an internal question
what about the actual existence and
production and power and influence over
that one version of record If there
really is
one um are you asking uh how reliable is
a versioning system uh like if there's
some kind of versioning system where the
user you know changes information is
there a reliable versioning system that
can keep track of all these changes is
is that yeah and even given a reliable
complete perfect git type versioning of
the
text how how does that not or does it or
Etc have conflict outside of the
text well I'm I'm not exactly sure what
you're asking but let me pose this
situation to you suppose that um I don't
know
um suppose that the that the system is
unclear about what the story is saying
and ask the user you know are is
bills are these two people related are
they
co-workers and the user responds the
user makes a response so therefore
changes the record changes the metadata
and says something really vague like uh
they're they they they know each other
that's the response that didn't really
address the question right like it
didn't resolve the issue that was raised
right but then so what that means is
that the story is simply vague right the
the story is not a maybe not a great
story it just has inconsistencies within
it it's it's uh not logical maybe or
it's just too vague to understand what
it what is being said so that's not the
is that's not the problem with it's not
a problem of cogar itself that's a
problem with the telling of the story
and its completeness and its logical
consistency and things like that and
just like any just like just if you and
I were in a room together and we're
hashing out what we think about some
situation I may I might make some vague
statement to you about you know people
involved and you might think in your
head what what is what is he saying and
you know like that's the way it is right
that's the way it goes and you might ask
me you know can you clarify that but
maybe I give you some unclear answer and
then you still don't know what I'm
saying and you walk away thinking well
John doesn't really know what he's
saying but that's the that's also can
happen here right so if I'm a user and
there's some a group that I'm
participating in and there's some event
that I'm offering a story to and I and I
submit some a story that is especially
if I have a history of submitting
stories that are unclear logically
inconsistent
incomplete you my reputation in that
group is probably not going to rise very
high you know people will eventually
figure out that he he doesn't he's not
clear on what he's saying you know or
else he doesn't know what he's
saying so you know those are that's
that's part of the Dynamics
interpersonal Dynamics and and the you
know assessing assessing who in the
group can be reli on to give a
thoughtful uh you know reasonably useful
contribution and who should we pay
attention to like the group has an
attention mechanism right naturally and
maybe even facilitated by cogar to some
degree and that attention mechanism
would sort of naturally focuses on
contributions from people who are known
to provide clear uh useful information
in the past or maybe people who have
good predictive capacity like maybe I
get a a Rec a record and a reputation
because I've participated in this group
many times or on many different events
and I a lot of what I said was going to
happen in the world actually happened
you know I'm good at making forecasts of
what's you maybe maybe I'm good at
making forecasts so maybe the group is
going to weigh my contribution a little
bit more than some other person's
contribution that was unclear or made po
forecasts so I maybe I maybe I kind of
didn't answer your question question
Daniel but yeah I I think it it touches
on and you site and discuss some related
projects related to like meta governance
like you talk about modular policy and
about attention economics and then also
the trust networks it's uh lot of
interesting work like John Ash's work in
cognism and just thinking about how the
attention distribution which is changing
moment to moment based upon what kinds
of message passes
and and Quantum reference frames the
interpretant deploys in that moment in
the information environment setting and
then how that relates to like formal and
informal and all these heterogenous
systems which I think will bring us
through the series towards active
inference and what does active inference
do Beyond you saying there's positive
alternative narratives however such is
some of the most common statements that
people implicitly or explicitly say
yeah well you have you raised many good
points uh I'd like to talk speak to a
couple of them uh one is that you know
by by by thinking of you know a group
decision- making as a cognitive process
and thinking of a cognitive process as
being a purposeful uh process and uh and
and using using active inference and
other uh uh Frameworks to potentially
you know evaluate how maybe there's ways
to evaluate how functional a given
process was maybe in retrospect a group
can look back at its history and assess
how functional is our cognition how how
how are we doing how how is information
flowing how what are the many you know
from a from a scientific standpoint what
are the many ways that we could evaluate
the process of cognition for its you
know capacity or functionality or other
things so you know those are some of the
nitty-gritty scientific uh questions
that that this project is sort
of uh offering in a way uh another thing
that you mentioned that I'm really glad
you mentioned was meta governance and um
uh it's an interesting group uh and I I
you know cite them in the first paper at
the end um but uh I did I did it
reminded me that I wanted to say that
that um you know cogar itself is sort of
a group agnostic
like different kinds of groups could use
cogar a cogar app and that that the
different groups might have different uh
you know levels of formality or
different ways they want to make
decisions maybe if it's a
decision-making uh you know process
they're interested in maybe they maybe
they want to use a majority vote maybe
they want to use rank Choice voting
maybe they have some other
you know unusual system they want to use
maybe they want maybe the group is
organized in a particular way maybe it's
an autocratic group or you know or a
very Democratic group or something right
so cogar could be used by any group the
group is going to Define what it is and
how it works and what its rules are and
you know how things go and then cognard
seeks to be the structure on which then
U you know uh Co cognitive event group
events can occur right and that is
really good because it doesn't cogar is
not responsible for you know uh forcing
all users to to use some particular
method or approach or rule set or
whatever you know there's room for
Innovation within the cogar system
there's room for experimental experiment
experiment within the cogar uh system
there's a history of of events uh that
can be assessed in hindsight for how
well they worked uh how did they how
well did they guide a group towards uh
shared uh you know widely widely shared
and uh valued solutions to problems and
things like
that so uh yeah awesome okay another
question from the live chat and anyone
else can continue to write questions and
we can continue to explore a few things
synthetic data generator wrote can it be
used as a protocol for group mental
model
harmonization well that's what it is you
know if I understand the question
correctly that's sort of what it
is um if you and I are together in a
room and we're talking about some
situation in the world I have a model of
in my mind about how how the world works
and what'll happen if we do something or
not do something and what it means and
what it's what the future might be and
you have the same you have a your own
model in your head and we're and we're
communicating aspects of that but what
but what cogar does is it kind of makes
that process available to the large
group setting where there's potentially
millions of people who are participating
in this and what it what it what it does
is it makes the model
explicit right it it puts it down in an
explicit way so that it can be assessed
and analyzed and considered as whether
it's different how different it is from
other ways of approaching the situation
or you know what its components are so
um you know I I I that is what cogar
does is it it it
represents a user's mental model of of a
situation yeah and I think an important
aspect of the harmonization ation is
whether or not any given sense of
harmonization is achieved or whether
that's like a positive attribute used
like coherence informally by taking like
a dynamical systems parametric modeling
basian probabilistic there actually are
ways like using fmri analysis on the
brain that rhythms of different time
scales different Mutual information
different Kale divergences like there's
a whole toolkit of harmonics and
Analysis so this is one mapping strategy
and
representation however it doesn't um
need to be the only mapping or
representation one that has some great
causal properties though and helps be
like kind of a repository format for the
perception cognition and action that
make things about a given system
specific rather than like the generic
active inference
formalism yeah there's a recently
there's been uh several papers published
on the how groups harmonize their belief
systems as they come together to you
know understand the world or make
decisions so um there's a already prior
work on uh what kind of what
harmonization in a group setting might
look like and how that works and how it
might be ma even mathematically
approached you know for modeling
purposes yeah and another another thing
that you just raised there a moment ago
Daniel is that is the idea of a
repository so suppose that cogar existed
and were you know say millions of
stories in cogar and you know hundreds
of thousands of group events that could
be analyzed in retrospect think of the
value that would be to science for
understanding cognition and
understanding uh you know how
information is conveyed and used and
flows and you know U what kind of
designs for rule systems or uh inputs or
whatever
facilitate uh nition in the best way I
mean the just the existence of a
repository of externalized belief models
of you know complex externalized belief
models of a variety of individuals on a
variety of topics itself would be
extremely valuable for cognitive science
and computer science and various other
you know psychology other various other
aspects of
science yeah this relates to a question
that synthetic data generator followed
up on it's an interesting question Lin
and Simon were the seminal researchers
in this diagrammatic reasoning is the
explicit model visual or
linguistic is the um um is if I can
interpret that the question is the story
graph visual or linguistic is that about
it
um uh so it's it's a comp the story
graph one of the purposes of the story
graph the meaning representation is to
allow
computation so um in that sense I guess
you would say it's linguistic it's it's
it's trying to um record the trying to
capture the meaning of what a you know a
phrase is what the user is trying to say
right and how that phrase relates to
other phrases of what what the user is
trying to say but it's also visual in
the sense that suppose and I'm glad you
brought this slide up but suppose I'm I
I I'm creating a story and now I want to
check whether the system is uh
understanding that story correctly right
so what I might want to do is I might
want to view a portion of the story
graph under the hood and see if the
system put those things together
correctly so that aspect could be sort
of visual as a user I could look at
something you know like this like what
you have on the screen and go like okay
I see that u i see that these two
concepts were properly connected with
each other it actually you
know Sue actually is related to Robert
in uh you know this particular way or it
was it was Sue that dropped the gun not
Bob or you know whatever the story is so
a use there might be visual tools that
the user would have available in order
for them to you know query the query the
underlining story graphs or even query
someone else's story graph you know
there might be visual tools for that and
and and a result from a query might be a
visual result so that you know it sort
of makes sense to how the different
elements are connected with each other
but the but the but the you know kind of
the core thing happening under the hood
is
computation uh based on the linguistic
meaning of of of phrases and and the
intent of the
user yeah a lot there especially
programs considered and graphs
considered as diagrams like from an
applied category theoretic perspective
the data structures themselves already
being diagrammatic symbolic now they
they might not be the right semantic
representations for given system with
this available observable with this
unobservable model for this person with
this accessibility that language like
Etc but that is a cognitive situation
with the human computer interface so
whether it's a phone and uses this
interface or uses another interface part
of the interesting question with a
generative model interoperability is can
those different blankets different
screens be also connected to a system
that has an underlying representation
that those perspectives come filtered
through right right right right you you
you raised um the field of Applied
category Theory there a minute ago which
is really interesting lots of
applications of Applied category to this
sort of setting because maybe you want
to translate this graph into some other
representation uh and you want to make
and you want to uh you want that that um
translation to preserve meaning well
that you know that that's a funter in in
um in applied category Theory so there
might be ways to use applied category
theory in in if even designing the
structure of this you know the under the
kind of like what structurally how does
a story graph work how what is it how is
it stored how is it retrieve from a
database and you know how is it
manipulated and how is it you know what
kind of functors translate a particular
story into a different version
or visualization or
or you know
uh
um really just a different
you different version of that story or
sub substory or translated from a story
graph into English or a story graph into
animation or you know like whatever the
case whatever the case might
be awesome well this was a great first
go fort one maybe just resta what are we
going to head towards and do to what
would be fun and what what for those who
are watching now could do between now
and
then yeah well um uh so we've today
we've kind of talked about the kind of
the general highlevel what is cogar and
what is it supposed to do uh next time
when we get together we'll talk more
about meaning representations and you
know
what what kind of you know what should
the cogar meeting representation look
like what should it do what what
characteris s should it have how was it
put together how does maybe we'll have a
chance to talk about how does applied
category fit into all of this and
um um in the meantime uh you know I W I
encourage Watchers to take a look at the
papers and uh and also if there's
questions um you know feel free to send
send questions I think I can be reached
through the Institute somehow perhaps
and um or post question and maybe we can
try to pick up any of those questions or
comments or suggestions you
know that are offered in the intermedium
intermediate part pick it up next
time okay awesome thank you again John
and Lee too so see you next time sounds
good
bye e